(音樂)
我坐在兩隻巨人的後面
非常令人感到害怕
你不看起來很害怕
我只是在假裝
只是在假裝
所以,李博士已經非常完美地總結了李博士的講座
我想簡單地講一下李博士的講話
我認為這三個肋骨
我只是在假裝
我沒有想到他會這樣說
所以我可能會錯誤
但是李博士選的這三個肋骨
有些許跟劇本有關
第一是關於神的形狀
第二是關於影響力的神的方向
不是說到最後
而是回到中心,回到神的圖案
最後可能是關於神的權力
李博士,關於這三個肋骨
你覺得他們好吃嗎?
我今天午餐的時候
我正在想著
我希望中國人會知道
有別的方法去切雞肉
而不是每一塊雞肉都要切成一塊
我想說的是
我嘗試說的
李博士說的話
在很多方面都很合理
因為我嘗試說的
這整個神話的理論流程
從一個開始到一個結局
當然不是否認
在這個理論的結構
有很多的轉變
有很多的事情發生
這些事實上
在某些時候
是一個故事的懸殊
例如,耶穌進入了死亡,然後再回來
還有,在神話和詩中
有很多的評論
這些都是好的
但我認為
雖然第一部分
斯蒂芬的觀點是
在古代的神話
這就是它的看法
但當你看到
這是一個故事
它在某個地方
它其實是帶領著耶穌
到結局的時候
我有時候對學生說
我們不應該去想
這個神話的故事
即使我把它放在
一個很長的直線
它只是一個大渠道
兩個直線在前方
在中間流動的水
它就像亞馬遜河一樣
亞馬遜河的渠道
那是一個非常複雜的水系統
水流向後
向後
渠道,湖,等等
但最後一天
水流都會向同一方向流動
那就是
那些水
在亞馬遜渠道
會在亞洲海洋中
這就是命運
我想說的是
在古代
就像亞馬遜河流
水流都會向著耶穌
和神的使命流動
這是我首先想說的
然後
我第二點
我認為和斯蒂夫所說的相符
當然
當聖經寫家
神父
說者
聖經寫家
寫到聖經
當他們想要看未來
他們總是回到過去
他們總是說
我們有一個神
已經做了一些很奇妙的事
但祂還是一樣的神
所以祂要再做一次
那最明顯的地方
在聖經最後一章
你無法理解聖經
不說祂一直
使用耶穌的語言
和古代的語言
來表達
我們有一個神
所以
這就是我前面的講座
一種講座
我說了
神的民族
是以記憶和希望為主
的
沒有記憶
你不知道自己是誰
這就是為什麼
在後成代的時期
內瑪雅人
會做很多
以保存記憶
這個人是誰
這是亞維的民族
是出口的神
當你有記憶
你會知道
你會有希望
因為這是你擁有的神
所以
那種不斷的被轉移
使用過去
為了未來的希望
是基礎
我認為我會同意
斯文的說法
這可以嗎?
你提到的一點是
希望不是基於
我們在遙遠的未來
但也有部分的希望
是基於
我們對神的工作的記憶
我對嗎?
是的
是基於記憶
但也有部分的
是在想像未來
這就是神父們所做的
他們以神的方式
創造未來
未來還沒有
當聖經96召喚
所有的創造
來慈祷
來慶祝
因為神正到來
他們正在描述世界
實際上
聖經描述世界
是一個平等的地方
正義和正義
和穩定
和慶祝
我們知道世界並非如此
但
聖經的預言
和諸侯的預言
能夠預見
未來的世界
基於他們知道
神的性質
和他們想要做的事
所以這是一種組合
記憶和想像
這總是會有
我可以繼續嗎?
抱歉
我必須抱歉
我把時間給你短了
不不不
沒關係
請說
我們無法想像
新的創造會是怎樣
除了聖經告訴我們
在聖經65召喚之外
這並不驚訝
因為我們還沒有到那裡
我們無法想像
我們已經超越了
我們生活在三個層次
的宇宙時間宇宙
和時間
耶穌
耶穌的復活體
已經在那三個層次裡
因為祂可以觸摸
祂可以吃
祂可以烤魚
但是祂也能夠
在那裡活動
消失
祂已經存在
如新創造的第一果實
新創造已經在這裡
這就是我和斯蒂芬的最後的意見
所有聖經說的
已經開始了
我們已經在那三個層次裡
生活了
我的最後的三角形
新創造
我再做一次
我把它再次傳遞到
聖經
我們已經在聖經和聖經之間
生活了
在神的新世界
已經在那裡
雖然我們無法想像
現在我用我的說法
我喜歡在聖經8
Paul在說
生命的形式
他說
全創造正在長大
是的
但是它正在長大
因為孩子的孕育
換句話說
新創造已經在
這個創造的胎兒裡
生育了
這是一個非常有趣的說法
因為這裡有一個原因
Paul在說
復活身體
你能想像
兩個胎兒
胎兒在胎兒裡
一個人對另一個人說
這是想像
你相信生命的復活嗎
我們聽到很多
關於光和氣息的謠言
你能呼吸嗎
你相信這些嗎
然後他就說
不不不
這只是一個謠言
只是為了讓你開心
這個胎兒就是所有的東西
沒有什麼比無精靈液更多
只要享受它
因為
吃喝住
結婚
因為明天我們會出生
我們結束了
OK
現在
你看
胎兒在胎兒裡
無法想像
胎兒在胎兒外面的情況
即使它有所有的能力
因為胎兒在胎兒裡
他們有眼睛
他們有耳朵
他們有腦子
他們有能力
活在一個世界
他們還沒想像到
這就是為什麼生育這麼傷心
OK
這就是為什麼我們會在胎兒裡
喊哭
因為我們突然
在光和氣息
和呼吸
有人在背後打擊你
讓你哭
現在
Paul說
新的創造
與生育不同
它是同一個人嗎
當然是
胎兒在胎兒裡
是同一個人
會生育
活在世界裡
但是生育是一個巨大的
變化的時刻
這就是為什麼我們說
生育的日子
我們知道你的生育日
不是你的出生日
即使你知道
生育的日子
即使你開始的時候
已經是九個月了
我們現在正在生活在
新創造的世界裡
的一種生育
我們還沒想像
它會是怎樣的
但這也不是原因
否認它會存在
因為神已經保證了
這就是我喜歡用的形容詞
幫助我們思考
這世界和下一世界之間的持續
同時也有著不持續的
這就像是
生育的胎兒
與生育的人
之間的持續
同時也有著不持續的
在生育的時刻
有幫助嗎
是的
是一種想像的想像
謝謝
這是一個很有幫助的例子
所以
李博士
我非常高興
繼續你對於
生育的說法
因為
我只不喜歡的一點
就是在你的題目中
你說
它們會在哪裡
結束
是的
所以對於生育
這不是結束
我喜歡CS Lewis的書寫
我第一次讀
他的《善於基督教》
是在我大學一年級
我不懂這個詞語
但是我後來
繼續讀《南亞》的《論述》
最後一段
最後一場戰爭
他描述了死亡的那一刻
是夏季的第一天
然後我才明白
這不是學校的年底
這是夏季的一年初
所以
它們在哪裡開始
所以謝謝你對於
這個生育的說法
我覺得這對兩隻胎兒的交流
對話很有幫助
我以為你說的是想像
我們要開始
而不是結束
所以這確實是
我認為
生育的關鍵
所以我不是說
這個世界並不重要
所以記憶
或整個聖經
是關於這生命
並不是關於未來的生命
但我們仍然在等待
這個生育的開始
我喜歡
謝謝
我們可以在這裡拍一部
荷里活電影
但是
你剛才說了
它什麼時候會開始
讓我開始懷疑
我會在哪裡
所以這是什麼
我認為
這就提出了
我們現在為了什麼而生存
你看
這就是我們的基督教學
其實非常重要
因為
如果我們看到的是新的創造
在這裡
如同聖經所說
不會有欺騙、謀殺、謊言、邪惡、腐敗
如果沒有了
就不會有了
換句話說
我們現在要活在
為了這生命而準備的那一刻
這不僅是在道德上
我必須要小心
如何活下去
因為我將會在天堂
或新的創造
這也意味著
這就是我
我沒有給足夠時間
對於我所說的
在《聖經》21:1
約翰說
他看到了國王們
帶著他們的光榮
他們的富貴
他們的榮耀
進入了神的城市
這意味著什麼
我認為這並不意味著
這只是會發生在
國王們和首相們
他們會活著
當耶穌回來了
他們將會前來
前往聖堂
在我們之間
我認為
它正在說
什麼是國王們和國家的
光榮和美麗
這是人類的
人類的
人類的文化成就
我們人類
能夠創造
巨大的
光榮和美麗
都被罪和自私
和自豪和憂愁
和無道
和慾望
但人類的成就
在神的形象中
是奇妙的
我認為這段話
告訴我們
新的創造
並不是一個
空白的座席
在那裡
神看著人類
所做的一切
在過去的十萬年裡
祂說
把所有的東西
放進垃圾桶裡
那是煙火的一切
讓我們開始新的創造
我認為
這會發生的是
神會把
人類的文化的光榮
和所有的邪惡
都吸進去
然後被毀滅
清洗和滅絕
在祂的判決中
這就是2彼得
三語
它會被燒掉
但燒掉的東西
並不是一個
宇宙的燭台
裡面沒有東西
只剩下煙火
而是一個
宇宙的煙火
裡面的東西
被吸進去
就是垃圾
就是罪
就是邪惡
而剩下的
就是人類創造的
光榮和美麗
在神的形象中
現在在新創造中
正在祝福神
這意味著什麼呢
意味著你的工作
每天的工作
對於人類的
會有所貢獻
在新創造中
我在這生的工作中
會有所貢獻
在神的新創造中
這給予了價值
給予了意義和意義
對於普通的每天工作
這本書寫了
由達爾·科斯頓寫的
叫做
"天地之好"
我認為這是它的名字
我們的每天工作
在這生中
會有所貢獻
在神將帶給我們的
新創造中
不要問我為什麼
我不知道
我明天要寫什麼報告
或者說
你需要做什麼
你需要煮什麼
我不知道
但是神有能力
來賦予和恢復
我認為這是一個
很勵志的思想
不只是
我們死後都會飛到天上
這比此更有信心
比此更有地道性
比此更有滿足感
所以我們在準備裝飾
這可能
你可以這麼說
我們肯定是
新創造的人口
已經在這創造中生活
這就是教會
我們是未來的人
我們在歷史的右邊
我們在神的故事中生活
所以現實世界並不在那裡
我們有時會談到
現實世界在那裡
不是
現實世界是神的世界
新創造
我們在生存中
我們已經在裝飾中
我們已經在貢獻
我們在賦予
國王和國家的榮耀
他們將會帶來他們的榮耀
這對一年級的理論學學生來說是非常有趣的
但我可以深刻地記住
我們在課堂上的討論
這給予了意義、意義
以及永恆的善良價值
給予了我們亂亂糾纏的感覺
這也是為何
我今天早上想與你們進行一個對話
我會提到路德的《道德法》的靈性使用
因為您已經非常深入地探討了
路德的原始法律
但路德先出手
他說:你無法做任何事
這是一場失敗
懺悔是指不要相信自己
這在於基督,是在於聖體
我覺得這就是希望的共同實現
我們盡力而為,但卻失敗了
但這就是聖經
這是天性
這是永恆
不是遠遠的未來
是天空的派
或是人類的opium
不,這是現實
我們今天正在體驗
我們知道這是真的
因為基督已從死亡中復活
這定義的時刻
並非在未來
這正是勒斯林·雅畢根說的
在復活中
復活只有意義在於
它是從何而來的故事
如果你嘗試去理解
基督的復活
如同新教義所描述
在任何其他世界觀
如在物質世界觀
死亡的身體不會復活
你只能以神話來理解
基督在復活的心中
或是在聖經中
有過一些靈性體驗
但墓地是空的
是基督的身體
從死亡中復活
這就是聖經所說的
你見到一個人復活
我們見到一個人復活
他們碰到他,吃了他,走過他
基督的身體復活
是新創造的開始
是基督已經開始的
因此,在基督教中
Paul可以說
我們已經與祂同在
Paul說的,在天堂
這要靠一大步的想像力
我還活在這個世界
我仍然是一個死去的罪惡人
在這個時代的複雜
我仍然活在這個古代
但我已經在這個緊張的世界
我已經在天堂的市民中
我已經在我的身體中
有了基督的生命復活
就如同Paul所說的
這也是為何
不僅是John堅持
基督的靈魂
說話變成靈魂
他也被提起了身體
但Paul也堅持
這就是他現在所活的
我所活的生命
是基督在我身體中的
我們是基督在我身體中的
我可以回到你的問題
關於法律的問題
我同意你的說法
當然,我認為
Luther和Calvin
在這裡彼此彼此彼此
Luther當然認同
法律的重要功能
就是它可以曝光我們的罪惡
但這不是因為法律本身不好
而是因為我們不好
這一點我們需要非常小心
因為Luther的懷疑
是要把法律曝光我們的罪惡
然後讓法律本身
變成不好的
我們必須要守護法律
Paul從來沒有這樣說
我們必須要守護罪惡
在聖經七章
他重複地描述法律
是那些是善、活、聖的
法律不是問題
問題是
當法律對付了罪
當法律對付了死
我們就會對它造成死亡
我重新想到一個說法
對於這個說法的意思
Paul其實問了一個問題
那是如何對生命造成死亡的
然後我想到蝦子
蝦子
抱歉,寶寶在胸前
但這是另一個畫面
因為我們都知道蝦子是好東西
是食物
是神的創造物
是充滿蛋白質的
但對某些人來說
蝦子會殺死你
但問題不是蝦子
問題是你的疾病
是在你身上
有些東西在你的身體裡
會反應蝦子
然後會殺死你
我想這就是Paul所說的
問題不是神的法律
這是善、活、聖、正、完美的
但問題是我們是罪惡的
我們拒絕遵守
所以法律在靈性的意義上
它會引導你去聖經
它會閉上你的嘴巴
告訴你你需要被救
但感謝彼得神
祂會讓我們得到這一點
然後是Calvin
他也說了
是的,這是真的
但法律也有三種用法
第三種是
法律仍然操作為指引
指明了我們如何活著
法律告訴我們
如何愛一個人
法律給我們設定的標準
模式、模式
如何活著
這就是我主要用法律的方式
在我的書中
我問
如果Paul說
所有的文章都是有用的
正如你所說
為正確訓練和正義
我沒有必要
說自己是一位教會人士
我相信所有的文章
都是由神啟發的
是有用的
除非我準備了
寫一章關於伊達基
或一章關於聖經
或聖經
這本文章
是神吸引的
是有用的
對訓練和正義的
我必須找到
這裡有些東西
在我對神的聲音
對神的呼吸中
在我對正義的訓練
能夠做到的方式中
能夠使我能夠
做到的方式中
即使我沒有
做到正確的訓練
因為我無法
我沒有牛角尖
在我的後座
在我背後
所以我無法遵守這個法律
正如它所寫
但是
這裏必須有些東西
神想通過它
對我說話
使我能夠
有神的聲音
這就是
法律
作為一個牆壁
作為一個鏡子
讓你展現你的罪行
讓你展現你的失敗
你需要聖經
但也成為了一個導導
讓你能夠
活在神的方向
謝謝
我想你們也提出了
各種話題
都值得追究
例如
我的觀點
是要
要被形容
但其實
我喜歡你的觀點
關於想像
是的
這是很真實的
記憶能夠幫助我們
有一個
有一個交換的想像
並不是固定在現實之中
但是
神是更加強大的
祂可以
做任何事
祂可以做更大的事
比你能想像的更大
所以
這就是我們
期待的一件事
但同時我們也知道
這不是我們能夠得到的結局
是的
老天爺也說過
神說
不要想起過去的事
就算你提醒他們
過去的事
祂說
我會做一些
會讓你們感到驚訝和驚訝的事
但是過去的事
仍然是祂所做的模式
所以
當耶穌第一次來
很多人都認出了
很多人沒有
即使他們有了經文
他們仍然驚訝
神會成為
納粹的耶穌
這個探頭的兒子
洗別人的腳
觸碰妖精
和原諒女性
你知道
神怎麼會
變成這樣
所以很驚訝
神會這樣做
所以這就是
我所想說的
當耶穌再次回來
會有很多驚訝的事
即使我們
知道經文的知識
我們仍然會發現
神會做一些
讓我們驚訝
我們從來沒有想到
謝謝神
祂比我們的想像更大
但祂給了我們我們的想像
就像那本
《諾貝爾》的書
《神的想像》
我們是神的形象
我們是神的想像
神要想像宇宙
然後說出它成為實相
神給了我們
這個想像的能力
我覺得這很明顯
是人類的
我們知道
狗和大象
不會想像
其他東西
很難說
他們會夢想
但我不知道
我們人類的能力
是站在宇宙和時間之間
去想像一些不同的東西
在人類歷史的偉大時刻
當時有很多的壓迫和痛苦
例如黑人奴隸
是由耶穌基督
和神所傳授的
寫信的想像
帶來的
尤其是在美國
黑人奴隸的流行
黑人的靈性
他們所說的
想像了約旦的未來
想像了去到康寧地區
想像了去到水裡
有非常多的
想像自由和自由
都是從
從古代的耶穌
尤其是從耶穌的死亡
這在歷史上
有很多次發生
神的人類
是記憶的人類
因此他們是希望的人類
當你有了過去的記憶
和希望未來的希望
你就是一個任務的人
因為你會問
我該怎麼生活
如果那是
我過去的事
而那是我未來的目標
那是一個
道德和任務的挑戰
我想我們應該邀請觀眾
參加我們的討論
你認為呢?
有問題的觀眾
請用麥克風
來問問題
或寫下問題
在紙上
傳給我
讓我可以
翻譯出來
(麥克風轉換中)
(英文)
謝謝你們
非常感謝你們
默哲偉
你們給我們畫了一張圖片
是一種想像
這是現實
但那是未來的事
我們被圖片觸動了
我們真的想要去那裡
但是當然
對於基督徒來說
如果我們只將希望放在未來
問題就會變成逃脫
我們想逃脫
所以這世界並不重要
所以我想默哲偉的訊息
是重要的
我們今天也看到了希望
即使是在過去
所以如果我想將你們兩人的形象
可能是像
我們的基督信仰
是基於一個
已經發生了
但還沒有實現的事
信仰是已經發生了
透過死亡和復活
但也並非完全滿足
所以我們已經在那裡
但還沒有實現
我想我們需要兩個
但當我讀《新經》時
作者們總是希望耶穌的復活
我認為原因是
其一是因為他們在受苦
所以他們無法找到希望
在地球上
我認為
當我們回到整件事的基督性應用
當我們面對一個真正的受苦的人
我們應該如何
如何與他們交談基督的希望
就像
現在你看到地球上還有希望
我們應該如何
我們應該如何更加強調未來
你明白我的意思嗎?
「已經」但還沒有的方面
已經在耶穌的教導中
在他的講道中
他將兩段講道放在一起
在一篇章中
我認為是在《路克》中
或者是在《馬克》中
他在講述基督的國王是怎樣的
他說
一方面
就像是種了柑橘子
它會長得很大
所以事情會開始變得小
所以不要擔心
如果一切看起來很不重要
只有耶穌和一位工匠
它是小的
但它會長大
另一方面
就是種了柑橘子的人
他起來
他去睡覺
他不知道發生了什麼
而柑橘子本身已經長大
並產生了種子
所以耶穌似乎在說
柑橘子已經種了
而神的國王也會長大
也會產生種子
所以已經有了
工匠已經做了他的工作
也有了未來
我認為新教的作家們
並沒有提到
耶穌的復活
因為他們只是在痛苦
並沒有希望
他們是在痛苦
但我覺得是因為
他們有了
復活的信心
這個耶穌
祢基督基督
祂將祂提出
從死去
並使祂成為耶穌
因此
祂現在是
天上的國王
如同聖經所說
未來也屬於祂
現在和未來
所以他們可以
走出一個世界
那時總是說
耶穌是主的
並說不
然後去死
因為他們願意
認同
世界的國王
已經被基督基督復活
所以我認為
新教的
已經和未來
你去看
在《聖經》中
那裡的約翰
在帕瑪斯的監獄
或許他自己在監獄
他可能只認識
幾個基督徒
在伊布萊斯斯
或者是其他地方
但耶穌給了他
這個視覺
基督復活
以及一種視覺
是所有的國家
族群
語言
It's a kind of tearing back of the veil to say this is reality.
There is a throne at the center of the universe and god is on it,
and there is a lamb who was crucified,
in whose hand is the scroll of the whole of human history,
and human history is under the control of the lamb of god.
And so he gives hope to the martyrs,
the suffering churches that he writes to,
because he sees the reality of the present glory of Christ.
I think that's the way the New Testament expresses it.
I don't know whether Stephen you want to add.
For the last 12 months or so,
or to be more precise,
since the national security law comes into place,
I kept asking myself,
why are we evangelical church leaders
are so afraid of suffering and persecution,
that we leave so quickly?
Of course there are exceptions,
but I remember,I recall back in the 80s,
when Eastern European Christians came out,
and the first question they asked,
why are you Western Christians not being persecuted all the time?
It's the other way around.
So in our faith,
is it a kind of do-it-yourself,
IKEA furniture building game?
Is all we are doing things,
when we cannot do anything,
then we gave up and leave?
Or is it a trust in the one true God,
in spite of our own,
was it frustrations, failures?
I think the Old Testament talks more about failures than success.
I don't know whether this is true in the Psalms.
I mean, you know, laments more than praises.
So you talk about the meta-narrative,
it's a story of failure.
It's not a story of success.
And you read the book of Acts,
it's not the church,you know,practicing mission,
but it's persecutions,it's arguments,
it's seal it,or whatever.
Among these realities,
the way of the Lord conquers the Roman Empire,
that seems to be the hope,
which again I would say not where are we going to end,
but here and now,
here in Hong Kong today,
or putting aside the sociopolitical,
moralistic reading of scripture,
but as a cancer patient,
I'm faced with this reality every day.
Oh, I hope someday,
no, no, no, no, no,
it's every day, every hour, every minute.
And so, yes, Christian hope.
I think I always want to ask New Testament colleagues
or theology colleagues,
ascetology, is it always in the future?
No.
I remember Carver Yu, our president emeritus,
once answered questions on our curriculum,
because some senior pastors raised his hands and queried,
CGSD doesn't have a course on eschatology.
And Dr. Yu stood up.
I was a dean.
I don't know how to answer as an Old Testament scholar,
but he is the theologian at CGSD.
So he stood up and said,
"Eschatology permeates every lesson."
Has he spoken the same to you?
I remember that statement very clearly.
So I suppose that is the Reformed tradition,
or the legacy.
And I think our church here in Hong Kong
really undergoing something that the Lord has prepared for us
and pushed us to reflect and review and self-criticism,
not criticizing the other side, but ourselves.
Can I add one thing about how,
during the present suffering or persecution or frustration,
how we may maintain hope?
I think the psalmic literature in this respect
helps us or provides us with a language
how we can talk to God in those times
so that we may uphold our hope
and uphold our hope in the one sovereign God
at the same time without
subcoming to the external pressures.
And I think this is one of the contributions
I think that's why psalms is so important.
I take it you teach the psalms?
Oh, sorry.
I don't mean to let you know about that.
Yes, why did you say what you really think?
I want to agree with you,
because I think the psalms are tragically neglected
in the Christian church.
When I speak, even sadly, of my own church,
All Souls Church, I keep on trying to get them
to use the psalms more often, to pray the psalms,
to actually sing the psalms from time to time.
Because the church through the ages,
the psalms were the hymn book for the church.
And as you rightly said,
the title of the book is "The Praises,"
and yet the largest category of psalms
within the book of psalms are laments.
But lament is not an absence of praise.
Lament, praise in the biblical sense,
is recognizing the reality and presence of God,
saying, "God, you are there,
and I will worship and glorify you."
But actually, God, at the moment,
life is pretty tough right here.
People are laughing at me, I'm suffering,
and you're not doing anything about it.
When are you going to do something about it?
I praise you, I love you, I trust you, I worship you,
but it's pretty bad.
So the psalms are willing to protest to God
about what's going on,
and there's nothing wrong with that.
I think, in fact, the idea that Christians
should always just be happy,
and never be angry with God
or never say anything negative,
that's not the way the Old Testament saints behaved.
They were quite willing to, it says,
beat on God's chest or to cry on his shoulder
and then to acknowledge him, to say,
"But God, I still trust you.
You're still there,
even though I don't understand what you're doing
or why you're letting this happen."
And so that is this balance
between recognizing that there's evil in the world
and wrong things are being done
and things are not the way we want them
and it's not comfortable
and we may be suffering,
and yet somehow being willing to say,
in all of that, God remains sovereign,
God has his purposes,
and God will remember his own people
and preserve them, ultimately,
even through death, even through martyrdom,
that you're safe in the hands of God.
So I think we do need to use the psalms more,
and that's what Revelation does as well.
It fills the book with the songs of the people of God,
celebrating the sovereignty of God,
even in the midst of the beasts and the empire
and the wrong things that are being done
by the kings and the nations
before the end of the world.
Thank you.
So, the next question.
Thank you, Dr. Rice and Dr. Lee.
The sharing of Dr. Rice on the FIFO forms
of hope, the hope of sinners,
of the nations and of creation
is truly inspiring.
And as you mentioned about new creation
repeatedly in this lecture,
and one important agent of the new creation
in the New Testament is the Holy Spirit.
But maybe due to lack of time,
you rarely mentioned the Spirit
in the previous lectures.
Yet, I believe the Holy Spirit
is the important agent of new creation
who reborn the Christians,
the John 3,
and transformed them into new creation in Christ,
2 Corinthians 5, verse 17.
And my question is,
I have two questions.
The first question is,
is the Spirit of God in the Old Testament
referring to the same agent
as the Holy Spirit in the New Testament?
Some biblical scholars prefer
to treat them separately
rather than equating them.
What do you think?
And the second question is,
you mentioned about the metanarrative,
the mission of God,
the story of God.
Can you outline the story of the Spirit,
the narrative of the Spirit
within your metanarrative?
Briefly, thank you.
Thank you.
My answer to the first part of your question is yes.
Yes, the Spirit of God
is the same Spirit of God
as the Spirit of Yahweh in the Old Testament,
who is sometimes called the Holy Spirit,
the Spirit of God's holiness,
and the Holy Spirit as we see in the New.
I'm absolutely convinced of that.
God is only one Spirit.
It is the Trinity.
We believe God is Father, Son, and Holy Spirit.
I've actually written a book called
Knowing God the Spirit,
Knowing the Holy Spirit
Through the Old Testament.
So you might want to look for that
because he is the Spirit of creation.
He's there.
He's the Spirit of justice.
He's the Spirit of...
Do you know who the first people
who are said to be filled with the Spirit are?
If you want to be filled with the Spirit,
the first people who are filled with the Spirit
are in the Old Testament,
in the Book of Exodus,
and they're called Bezalel and Aholiab.
You should know those guys.
They were artists.
They were craftsmen.
They were there to work with wood and stone
and fine metals and precious stones
to build a tabernacle.
The God whose Spirit had done creation
with all its beauty
now pours the same Spirit on these men
to be the artisans of the tabernacle.
It's a beautiful thought.
And then he's the Spirit of justice.
He's the Spirit of the prophets and so on.
And it's also the Spirit who is poured out
in the eschatological vision of new creation
because Isaiah speaks about God
pouring out His Spirit on the land
and restoring His people.
And of course, so does Joel.
And Peter quotes from Joel in the Day of Pentecost
that this is that which the prophet Joel spoke about.
So the idea that Spirit is different
in the Old and New Testament
wouldn't stand up to the Day of Pentecost
where Peter equates.
In relation to the metanarrative,
I would want to put my hand up and say,
yes, you are right.
That is an element that I should bring in more clearly,
namely the role of God's Spirit in the story
and the role of the Holy Spirit in Christian mission.
So forgive me for not emphasizing that as much as I should
because I think you're right.
But I want to say that the Spirit is there
throughout the whole of the narrative, isn't it?
The Spirit is there in the second verse of the Bible.
The Spirit of God is hovering over the waters,
over the deep there in creation.
And the Spirit of God is there in the ministry of Jesus.
He is filled with the Spirit.
He is conceived by the Spirit.
If I, the Spirit of God is doing the work.
And also, Hebrews says that even the work of atonement
is the work of the whole Trinity
because it's through the Holy Spirit
that Jesus offered Himself to the cross.
So the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit
are united in the work of atonement.
And then, of course, the Spirit comes
in the book of Revelation.
The Spirit is there before the throne of God
and engaged in the work of new creation and so on.
So that's something I should factor in.
And thank you for the reminder.
And I wouldn't want in any sense to have overlooked it,
Him, the Spirit.
But I should have perhaps mentioned it more than I did.
But it's certainly something which, again,
is cross-testamental.
It would be another uniting theme
within who we are and why we're here
and how we should live.
Well, who we are, we are created by the Spirit of God.
And how we should live?
Well, by bearing the fruit of the Spirit,
by being filled with the Spirit,
by living our lives in the Spirit and so on,
walking in the Spirit.
Thank you.
(英文)
Steven, you are the one who talked about
biblical theology and dogmatic theology.
And, yeah, there is obviously a difference,
but you explain it.
Well, I think at the risk of being
over-simplifying things,
I would say dogmatic theology or Christian theology.
Christian theology, yeah.
By theology, logos of theos,
we are talking about logic.
So today we talked about systematic theology.
Systematic is logical.
But going back to the Old Testament,
I don't claim to know the New Testament
as good as the Old Testament.
But talking about the Old Testament,
it's never logical, never.
Who stopped?
What do you say?
The Amazon River with all the undercurrents upside down.
Yes.
That's a challenge.
My understanding of the phrase biblical theology
means the theology of the biblical texts
seen in their own context and background.
So one could speak about, say,
the theology of Ezekiel
or the theology of the Pentateuch
or the theology of the Old Testament.
It's thinking what is the Bible saying
about God and God's action in the world.
And you were right, as James Sanders said.
Was it James Sanders?
The whole is about what God is doing,
not about us.
God is the main character.
That's why I like the idea of it being a drama
in which God is the director
and the chief author of the whole story.
So biblical theology is the theology
as articulated when we try to explain
what the Bible is saying.
Systematic theology is the way
in which we then try to put that together
into categories such as, well,
what is our doctrine of God, of creation,
of humanity, of sin, of salvation?
And so we create a kind of conceptual framework
for the Christian faith
based around those biblical theology
So systematic theology has to be rooted
in what the Bible says,
but in a sense it's trying to organize it
into a more conceptual framework.
But here is what I want to say
is that to me, all that we put
into our systematic theology
flows from the grand meta-narrative
of the Scripture
because it all comes out of that great story.
It tells us there is one living God.
He created this world.
He made us in His image.
We rebelled and fell against Him, fell into sin.
God chose to redeem us,
so He had to atone for our sin.
So it leads you to Christ,
leads you to the cross, the resurrection,
and ultimately the future.
So our doctrines are in a sense
an articulation of the implications
of the biblical story
and what it is telling us
about God and the world.
The two need to mesh together.
There is also a sense in which,
and maybe this is why CGST moves to put,
teach systematic theology,
teach dogmatics first,
and then see how the Bible critiques
and explains it,
is because the early Christian fathers
talked about the rule of faith.
They said that there is a way
of understanding the Scriptures,
which comes from the Scriptures,
but it's possible to read the Scriptures
in a way which distorts their meaning.
You could, as we all know,
you can make a Bible text
mean whatever you want.
You can take verses and passages
and you can really say things
based on a single verse,
which would be quite contrary
to what the whole Bible says.
Prosperity Gospel does that all the time,
for example.
And what the fathers were saying is
we need to read each passage of Scripture
and each book of the Scripture
in consistency with what the whole
of the Bible has to say,
the whole canonical rule of faith.
That's why there's a commentary series
by Zondervan just in the process
of being produced called
The Story of God Bible Commentary.
I've contributed the volume on Exodus.
I don't know if it's in the bookstall downstairs,
but the idea of the series is
that each commentator will work
on the text of that book
in the light of the story
that has gone before
and the story that follows.
In other words,
setting the text in the light
of the canonical Scripture,
especially, of course,
as centered on Christ.
And I think that's a very biblical way
of reading the Bible itself,
because it's what the Bible does.
They keep on telling us the story
as they go through.
So biblical theology, Christian theology,
they are ultimately the same,
but they're just different ways
of organizing and expressing
what we believe as Christians from the Bible.
Is that fair enough?
Something like that.
I just want to add one footnote.
A long one?
No.
Is it logical?
No, it is not logical,
because you talk about metanarrative,
the Bible story.
I would just want to add biblical poetry
or in Brueggemann's Old Testament theology,
the counter testimony
or Robert Davidson's
The Courage to Doubt.
You know what I'm saying.
I mean, it is not just the logical,
the positive,
or even the triumphalistic way
of reading Scripture into theology
and faith and work.
No.
It's actually,
I like your word, struggle.
It's a struggle.
And during the struggling,
you discover it's God,
the only one true God.
So you are not working for your salvation.
It's grace.
It's sola gratia.
So this is the Bible.
Yes.
I don't want to give the impression
that I'm looking down upon
systematic theology.
My first theological degree,
divinity training,
I did a double major in Old Testament
and systematic theology.
And then I moved on to my THM
in historical theology,
then coming back after playing truant
to Old Testament doctoral research.
So I suppose dogmatic theology,
historical theology,
systematic theology,
really helps, as you say,
categorizing the content of Christian faith.
But still, when you open the Old Testament,
it doesn't begin with, you know,
systematic theology,
existence of God.
Instead it says,
only fools will say there is no God.
So...
I think, Stephen,
with this word "metanarrative",
I would emphasize the meta bit of it,
because although I drew that diagram,
a nice straight line,
nice symbols and so on,
I don't want to say that it's all just story,
that it's all just narrative.
The whole point about a metanarrative is that
here is an overarching canonical shape
to the scripture,
which has a beginning and an ending,
which is a new beginning at the end.
And within that canonical metanarrative,
of course,
there are all kinds of counter movements
and questions and problems and struggles.
And that's why I love a book like Ecclesiastes,
which I've written a small exposition of.
It's coming out next year.
Because what Ecclesiastes does,
and to some extent Job,
but especially Ecclesiastes,
it says,
Look, I know that this is what God says,
and I know this is what wisdom should be,
and I know it's better to be righteous
than to be wicked,
and it's even probably better to be alive
than to be dead,
although you can't really tell
when you look at a dead dog.
It's just as dead as a dead human.
So, you know,
he's facing the fact that he knows
with his head what's true,
and yet he struggles
with all the stupidities,
the absurdities,
the futilities of life,
and he just puts the two together
and says,
What do you think?
And it's a wonderful book
of sort of questioning faith.
And I use the word questioning
both in the sense of it is
questioning the faith he knows he has,
because the book still comes to the fear of God,
but it's also a faith
which has the ability to question.
And so in my book I say
just because we're Christian believers
doesn't mean that we don't have any questions,
but also just because we're Christian believers
doesn't mean we have all the answers
to all the questions we have.
Sometimes we don't have answers.
That's why I wrote a book
called The God I Don't Understand,
because there are many things
you don't understand about God,
but it's okay.
There's a lot I don't understand
about my wife,
but that doesn't mean I don't know her
and love her and trust her.
She's a person,
and you don't always understand other people,
but you can love and trust them.
And so you can love and trust and know God,
even though there are things
beyond what we can really understand,
even when we have to say,
God, why did you allow that?
We don't know why.
And so that's true.
The Old Testament has this wonderful capacity
to affirm the truth,
but also to put the truth into the furnace
of questions and doubt and suffering
and lament and protest
and still come out the other side
as faith in the sovereign goodness of God.
I want to say a final word
before I stop.
Thank you for quoting very often
from the Book of Isaiah,
the prophecy.
The poetic commentary
rather than the storyline part
of the Old Testament.
I think that shows your meta narrative.
It's not simply narrative or storyline.
So thank you very much indeed.
Yes, I think that is a good question
to close the whole discussion.
Well, actually, I suspect
I'm just doing a reading response reading
of that question.
The person asking,
a Christian, our Christian theology
actually, may have something in mind
that a theology that has to be unifying,
unitary, and that can maybe
can include everything.
But perhaps what we are led to explore
is actually we may have
political theologies, if I may say.
And there are actually different trajectories
within this meta narrative.
And we do look forward
to your coming books
to lead us to scale
along all these trajectories again.
So once again,
our warmest applause to Dr. Wright
and also Dr. Liu.
謝謝大家.
(CC字幕製作:貝爾)
MING PAO CANADA | MING PAO TORONTO